hello welcome this is active inference
guest stream number
98.1 on February 10th
20125 we will be discussing active
inference in human computer interaction
with the authors of this very
interesting paper so thank you all for
joining and I'll pass to the authors for
their introduction and presentation
thanks again looking forward to
it I'm rodri muray Smith I'm a professor
at the University of Glasgow um and the
pi of the the European research Council
project that's funded this work the defy
project John I'm John Williamson I'm a
senior lecturer here at the University
of Glasgow and also one of the
investigators on this project and I'm
Sebastian Stein I'm a research fellow
here clco and also one of the
investigators on the
project yeah okay so we were um we um
published on archive a review paper on
active inance and human computer
interaction and then the um the friendly
team at the Active inference Institute
said oh would You' like to give a talk
on this so we're very honored to be
included in the um in the institute's
presentation so we're going to give an
overview of it but if you want to see
things in more detail then the at the
bottom of the screen you can see a link
to the archive
um
publication okay let's get
going so we'll cover a bit of motivation
for the work describe active inference
in HCI what the core elements are we'll
give an example of a particular case
study and ordinal selection which
Sebastian will present um and that's
work that we
um presented in Oxford at the Active
inance Workshop we thought it would be
useful to have some concrete examples as
part of the paper as part of the
discussion here and then some of the
challenges for applying this work in the
uh context of human computer
interaction oops so a little bit of
background about where this is all based
um we started um a year ago the the
fiveyear project called defi
um designing interaction Freedom with
active inference and the idea was we
wanted to look at how we could better
build the flexible interfaces of the
future that would use richer sensing
machine learning um in novel ways um and
that has three main elements active
inference is going to be the framework
for building things we wanted to use an
approach called optimal mechanism
designed to build the interaction
mechanisms that could combine Rich
sensing machine learning tools and embed
content into computational
structures and we wanted these
mechanisms to also have shared autonomy
mechanisms so that the um amount of
Freedom the computer would have could be
adapted so what we'll be talking about
today is the first part of this activity
on active
inference so there's a bit of background
for the motivation you can think about
you know how have humans gone about
um controlling the world around them you
know the very
first uh tools would just be simple you
rocks and things where the human could
use their muscle power to pick up a rock
and do something more than with their
bare hands as time went on we had tools
which would give us some more feedback
about the world that the actual um
this design of a chisel might be make it
easier to feel the texture of the wood
that you were working with and then
further development got us to take
external power and modulate that so that
could be wind power or steam power
there's some external source of power
which we could use to adapt our
tools but recent years have moved
towards the insertion of external
computational power and you can see the
um
um the framework that we're working with
here and the gray boxes in this figure
are where computational power has been
inserted so the human can act on an
interface they can perceive the
interface uh and that that computer that
they're interacting with can also
control the world so this could be a a
smart car and it could be tracking the
road with its own cameras and augmenting
the control to the the steering wheel um
but it can also be looking at human and
try to infer their attent it could be
augmenting the display so we have a a
closed loop interaction with the world
and the tool has got external
computational power algorithms
artificial
intelligence so the argument would be
that for Less effort the human could
achieve the same or more performance and
that's kind of a summary of you know
what the here the AI was actually
standing for artificial intelligence
rather than active inference you can
take one of these old Don Norman graphs
where you're plotting the amount of
effort you have to put in against the
performance and
usually um the lower line would be human
alone so usually you have to put a fair
amount of effort before you get any sort
of performance out adding artificial
intelligence or algorithmic support can
lower that threshold so you can get
something for far less but it's always
worth having a think about where that
Gap is being Filled from you know is it
an earlier version of you that's somehow
been learned or is it uh
um other people like you according to
some measure or is it a more malevolent
input from whichever service you're
using which is trying to nudge you the
way they want you to be so anyway it's
worth thinking about that background to
Tool design we're saying that humans are
now starting to need to use artificially
intelligent tools or algorithmic tools
so these are going to be the most
complex things that we've used to date
and the tools are no longer going to be
passive extensions of ourselves they're
going to be active Partners where
they're starting to take on certain
tasks and interaction becomes more of a
dance than a command and control one so
active inference appears highly relevant
as this element of active
tools okay also as part of the context
there was we think there's a a bit of a
crisis in HCI so you've got uh key
researchers like corn and wser
highlighting that we have concepts of
interaction that talk about design but
we fail to produce theories and Concepts
that have high determinacy and adequate
scope so they can't really do anything
in detail and they're not or they're not
broad enough if they can do something in
detail we haven't in HCI been seeing the
sort of ratcheting up of performance
that you see in subjects like machine
learning and computer vision where
people are sharing software and building
on each other's work and there are key
questions about agency which is core to
understanding um how we're going to be
relating to algorithmic support but how
do we go about measuring that how do we
go about checking whether our agency is
being taken away from us by
computers so given that active inference
is a closed look computational theory
for modeling agent Behavior it seems
very relevant to discussing these
questions so you've got this ele elegant
unifying Theory it's allows us to
incorporate machine learning basing
inferencing Pro probabilistic
programming and dynamic system
and we can work from lowlevel physical
interactions to high level reasoning
decision tasks so it seems like it's a
potentially going to be something that
could support the next generation of
human computer
systems so three elements that are
relevant for that is in human computer
interaction you've got a lot of
uncertainty humans are very variable
their context is complex and variable so
we need to have models that can quote
with uncertainty AC of inference is
probalistic and Views agents as entities
performing Basi and inference so that's
quite appropriate humans are also
intelligent agents they're inherently
predictive they're trying to understand
the world around them and act in a way
that is based on predictive models
active inference supports this sort of
analysis so we have a predictive
element and we also want to balance the
exploitation of the knowledge that we
have with exploration to try and reduce
future uncertainty and that's something
which um active inference gives us
support on as well unifying the uh
reasoning about perception and reasoning
about actions in a single
framework so let's get into active
inference in HCI so your traditional
active inference framework was often set
in a more natural context rather than a
design context so you might have an
intelligent agent in this case we have
our human user but it could be any other
biological agent and it's interacting
with an
environment and it's uh as action States
and it can senses environment and make
predictions about what is going to sense
given its actions on that
environment so with active inference in
a human computer interaction context
there are several major configurations
here um three you've got an active
inference model of the human interacting
with some system it could be anything so
when we're saying system we're talking
about the computer and its
interface um you could have the computer
and its interface represented by an
active inference model interacting with
a user who's unknown and you could have
the active inference model
transducing the information between the
user and the
computer
so we can split things up into offline
and online use
so the description approach is saying
we've got a model of a user o operating
under active principles to reason about
how um the user is going to
behave um you could have and there with
the system is just its environment and
you could use that at design time to
simulate user behavior and optimize your
designs or you could have it um um
evaluation time to interpret observed
interaction behaviors
Mutual interaction is where we're
modeling both
the um agent human agent and the
computer agent so we're looking at a
model of the whole interaction Loop and
we have two interaction agents working
together so here you
see uh one agent has become the
environment for the other so the human
motor states are then perceived by the
computer sensor States and the the
computer's action States could be
changing its display making noises
sending vibrations moving a robot arm
and these are perceived by the
perception states of the
user okay so that's you know the major
change from the usual presentation is
we're designing the environment of the
of One agent uh with another
agent okay in terms of um
online um options we've got a user
interact in directly with the active
inance agent this is a
constructive approach um and it can be
predicting the user's uh behavior and
acting appropriately so the user is part
of the environment but might not be
explicitly modeled in terms of theory of
mind we'll get to that in a second and
the other one is the transduction one so
you can have an active INF agent lying
between a user and an existing system so
it's mediating their action and neither
of them are explicitly assumed to be
active inference agents so the user and
the system jointly form the environment
of the mediating
agent um and all of the models that
we've been discussing so far could be
augmented by explicitly incorporating an
active inference model of the partner
within their generative former forward
model so we've called this a reflective
approach you're constating an active
inference in um system that incorporates
an active inference
model of a user so you see the embedding
of the another active inference model
within its um system
predictions and this ties into work
that's been going on in other areas of
um work and theory of Mind in terms of
levels of mental modeling where you
could basically have different levels of
higher order cognitive modeling of
mutual series of Mind between humans and
agents so we're now going to go back to
the transduction oops uh work that we
mentioned here and have a specific um
use case so Sebastian do you want to
take over yeah so um this is a use case
where we look at what's called noisy
ordinal selection um so in this case we
were looking at using active inference
as a as a transducer as what suggested
as one of the options that uh we might
want to use active entrance for in human
computer interaction um and this is work
that we presented at the Active
inference workshop last year in in
Oxford next
SL so um here we're looking at a rather
abstract human computer interaction uh
setting where which you can think of as
a a two- player game where one player in
this case the user would think of a
number and the other player in this case
the interface attempts to to Guess that
number and presents one number in each
interaction time step back to the user
where the user could then give feedback
in the form of saying that the number
that they're thinking of is either
higher or lower than the number
presented but that feedback is then
corrupted by some amount of noise where
uh the feedback Bel low might be flipped
into feedback higher and and vice versa
potentially with different rates um and
that's a that's a sort of scenario
that's rather relevant for uh sort of
naturally ordered symbols like alphabets
or sort of imposed orderings like we
have in in things like drop- down menus
um and the sort of Channel
characteristics of having uh very noisy
feedback is quite commonly um seen in
interfaces like brain computer
interfaces or other assistive
Technologies like um
electrography where we usually have
rather low um classification rates and
have to deal with um high levels of
noise but we have the possibility to
have uh rather noise free sort of
feedback in the form of a display back
to the
user so here's one example of how an
interaction might unfold over time so
time is on the x-axis here and the uh
the different uh the targets presented
to the user indicated by the agents uh
Trace in uh presented by the blue line
here um in this case the user is
thinking of the number four and then the
first time step all the way on the left
the agent or the interface is presenting
to the user the number 16 the user
feedback is indicated by the the
triangles pointing up or down indicating
that the feedback received by the
interface was either lower as in the
case of this first time step or higher
as in the case of the second time step
what you see here is that I think in
time of five it is where the feedback
given by the user is the first corrupted
feedback um at which point the agent
flips effectively its exploration area
to sort of higher um the higher numbers
uh and we'll see later why that is and
um in particular here the agent flips
its belief to be one where the user is
responding with comparably high error
rates but we see that over time the
system recovers and the agent can
actually correctly infer that the user's
Target is at or near um the the true
Target number
four next SL
[Music]
okay so there are some classic
information theoretic approaches that we
could apply here and which have been
applied in in previous work um but they
are only optimal under a set of strong
assumptions for example horin posterior
matching algorithm um is only applicable
if we assume that the noise is actually
IID uh fixed and known in advance um and
that the symbol set is arbitrarily large
as well as the feedback Channel being
Noise free so we were interested in
seeing whether active inference can help
relax those
assumptions in order to do that um we
translated the problem yeah if you can
the next SL we translated the problem
into an active Insurance
formulation uh where um we represent the
users intended Target as well as the um
the error rates as the the latent state
of the system that we would like to
infer um and the observations that the
agent can make about the system it's
reasoning about the user um uh are the
these binary feedback uh symbols which
correspond to their number being lower
or higher than what the agent has uh
displayed and the agent action uh space
is effectively the set of symbols that
the user might want to uh wants to
select in order to apply active inurance
we need probalistic forward models of uh
the system the agent interacts with
which in this case is the of State
transitions of the this latent State um
as a function of the the agent action in
the previous state so that's kind of
answering the question how might the
users Target and the noise vary over
time and we need a probalistic forward
model of how the user feedback is
generated answering the question what
symbol would I observe if the user
intended to communicate that they're the
target they're thinking of is higher and
so in order to uh select the next setion
we need to enily tradeoff between
learning about the user's intent and
learning about uh the environment
characteristics or the error rates of
the
channel so commonly we use gaussian
distributions to represent the belief
about the the latent state in in active
inance agents but ging distributions are
not particularly helpful here um that is
because a sequence of user interactions
is usually compatible with distant and
mutually exclusive beliefs um so if we
take an example where uh the agent
displayed the number 20 and the feedback
received was uh that the users's number
is lower than that and that is
compatible with their users's target
actually being lower and the Channel
having a rather low error rate R but
it's also compatible with a scenario
where the user Target is actually higher
and the channel has a high error rate so
in order to um represent a potentially
large number of these modes in our
belief distribution we decided to
implement a a particle filter where the
belief distribution is then a a weighted
combination of um um of Point masses in
this uh um uh space of uh
of latent States um but the kale
Divergence can still be computed rather
efficiently and quickly just by using
the multinormal distribution represented
by the weights in this
case
um so going back to the example that we
saw in the beginning um I want to now
look at how the agent reasons about the
latent State uh in particular the error
rates um and the user Target and we're
going to first look at the the error
rate which in this case we assumed to be
symmetric so it's equally likely to flip
a signal lower into one that's
suggesting that the target is higher and
vice versa and here you can see um
around the time step where the first
errors occur um the agent belief about
the error rate uh is sort of changing
from a lot of mass accumulated near the
the lower error rates to mass and the
relief distribution um aggregating
around High error rates so I should have
said before um the color in this case
represents the the probability density
within sort of local regions around the
sort of discretized levels of of error
rate um and the true error rate in this
case is 20% as indicated by the the red
dash line um and so over time we see
that the agents belief about the error
rate converges to somewhere close to the
true to error rate of the
system next one um now looking at the
marginal a distribution about the user
Target um we see that initially the
agent has rather broadly spread out um
density meaning that there's relatively
low evidence for specific targets over
the first few time steps but as the
agent learns more and more about uh the
error rate with which the user is
communicating it's unable to identify
the target correctly towards uh
interaction step 35 and
onwards so so we did quite a
comprehensive uh set of um
evaluation uh experiments which are um
detailed in the paper but just to
highlight a few here I want to present
first what we've done in terms of
simulating experiments and then present
some of the key results um so we're
always assuming that the channel
statistics are symmetric in this case
just to simplify the analysis um and
we're looking at scenarios where the
user could select between one out 32
different targets
um and we repeated simulations where the
simulated user actually uh imagines each
of the 32 different targets 10 times um
and simulated for 500 interaction time
steps where after each every 100 time
steps we reset the distribution of the
user targets to be uniform which uh is
simulating the behavior of a five
successive interaction
episodes um so one of the uh main
findings is that even in the absence of
knowing about the the error rate of the
the communication channel the active
inference agent can uh make decisions as
well or better than uh the Horan
algorithm that I've alluded to earlier
um after the first 300 time steps when
the agent has learned enough about the
error rate to to
compensate and we've also done some
experiments indicated on the on the
right hand side of this this slide where
we looked at the error rate actually
changing over time um and again with the
heat map displayed here you can see that
the agent agents belief can track the
the the changes in the in the true error
rate of the user so just to summarize um
here we presented a concrete example for
using an active inference agent to to
Reliable one of end selection um and
showed its Effectiveness in inferring
both the control polarity and the um and
working with non-stationary
statistics and we can bring in
additional assumptions and further
domain knowledge in that in a setup
that's might more specific than than
this one thank you okay so let's talk a
bit about core elements of active
inference in
HCI so the key aspects of an active
inference agent um are listed below
we've already discussed um the idea of
the agents and what entities are going
to be modeled and implemented as INF
agents the users the systems both
neither we need to look at the role of
the environment is it just a
transmission medium between the the
agents is user using the system as an
instrument to act on it or they both
fighting environmental flux
operatively we want to tie in some
discussion about Mark of blanket how do
we separate Agents from their
environment work out the actions that
each agent's capable of and be able to
Define boundaries between the user and
the system
forward models are obviously key to
active inference so we have to be able
to create a generative forward model and
that's often going to be an
implementation step that's very
challenging and because we have to be
able to predict future States synthesize
the observations that we would
see we're going to look at how we
predict and reason about the next spe
action because we need to use the
forward predictive models to estimate
future States and predicate actions on
the
estimates um
uh we have to think about the preference
P prior structure because the agents
goals or desired are going to be defined
as a distribution rather than as a
single um reference value or control law
so we're going to have to think about
how we can shape these priors to align
with the goal of interaction design so
it's this change from trying to describe
the natural world to trying to design
and create a a system or a world that's
going to be better for the humans
involved
and then there's all the Practical
implementation questions around building
and training the forward model
implementing your your rollout policy
getting your inference mechanisms to
work uh and perform basing updates and
the challenges associated with that so
let's start with the
environment here's a sort of cartoon of
the basic ways in which um the
environment can play a role you might
have the user in the system was directly
engaging with the environment can they
do this manage the variability in the
environment cooperatively so an example
of that could be that you might be
trying to use a Smart speaker uh and the
users try to operate that to change the
mood and observable behavior of a party
in their flood uh but the user can also
interact directly with others in this
party and they can bring their
observations of that together to pick
the next best track similarly a central
heating system might be might have an
application for controlling the
temperature in the building but the user
and also make changes like opening or
closing
windows we might have a trans
transmission approach so that we
are um just VI describing the
environment in terms of what to what
extent it affects the communication
between the user and the system so if
you have an environment with lots of
background noise then any audio display
by the system may be difficult for the
user to hear similarly bright sunlight
on the the screen might make the screen
invisible to the user so we need to
understand the impact of the environment
on the communication between the user
and the
system we may have the user applying the
system as some sort of intermediary
instrument to act on or better sense the
environment so it could be transducing
transducing user unobservable
information from the
environment um or it could be acting on
the environment at the behest of the
user we uh haven't discussed multi-agent
environments but they would be a a
natural um follow on where we start to
have multiple explicitly modeled agents
um acting
together
okay an interesting question in HCI is
where the boundaries are and obviously
the active inference Community has
focused quite a lot on the notion of
Mark of
blankets um but HCI has often struggled
a bit with this so the very name human
computer interactions suggests that
we're assuming there's a clear boundary
between a human and the
computer um and people might
often potentially naively associate that
with Clark's skin bag around the the
physical limitation of the
human um and we know that if you're
going to understand a system then
finding the boundaries between that
system and its environment seems to be
essential for analysis of it but these
the of blankets that describe the limits
of
um One agent may change dynamically as
we give and take control that could be
driven by technology so we might give a
user a tool or an assist of technology
and we can transform what they can act
and sense so that you if you have
somebody wearing augmented reality
glasses or virtual reality then we can
change how they're interacting with the
world we can let them see things that
would otherwise be invisible and we may
be able to give people the ab ability to
act in the world in a different way so
modern tools will have Contex sensitive
algorithmic support from algorithms from
Ai and these could augment the user
cognitively or it might relieve them the
need to attend to or or check on mundane
tasks and so that could be seen as
taking or augmenting agency depending on
how it's designed but basically you can
imagine that as we're taking over tasks
from the human that the the the uh
states which previously were being
controlled by them are now being handed
over to the agent to um work on so we're
seeing that an adaptation of the mark of
blanket depending on how much support
we're giving the
human so um we've you know been evolving
human tools from rocks to AI as we
mentioned earlier we're getting this
trajectory of increasingly powerful
effort leverage doing things better
doing more new things and so that means
that we're increasing our individual and
collective intelligence we're extending
our natural selves with our
tools um and although we started off
with crude functional tools like Hammers
and axes we move to tools which have
controllers in them like thermostats and
Governor Technologies based on um on a
controller approach and then each time
you're giving some of your agency away
for understood outcomes and the tools
can take on more and more of our tasks
asks but the question is um are we at a
point where we're potentially giving up
really important bits of
ourselves okay so arguments have been
made in the active inference community
that to maintain the Integrity of the
anent an needs to change and there's
several papers making arguments about
that that you need to adjust yourself as
your as your environment changes in
order to keep your internal States
stable um
and we looking at um the basic approach
that we were showing earlier we have the
the mark of blanket with its sensory and
actuation nodes internal and external
States but I think one of the
interesting things that we could be
pulling in from machine learning is the
notion of attention so that at different
points in the interaction cycle the
human may be actually only paying
attention to a very limited subset of
the sensory state so we have an
effectively different Mark of blanket
even though the human could potentially
perceive things on the the states that
they're ignoring and this can of course
be structured into a hierarchical
setup so this use of attention means
that we could be tracking you with our
closed loop models we could be going
through interaction processes and
looking at what the human pays attention
to using the standard BAS
methods to infer Mark of blankets at
different points in time and see what is
the human ignoring at certain time
points and what does that mean for
system
design other research within
HC um has been raising similar questions
Al not not from an active inference
perspective so there was a paper by um
saner and Jones um at MIT and one's a
computer scientist in an HCI context the
other's an um an anthropologist and they
were looking at intelligence as agency
and looking at diads of co-used agents
and looking at the line of control
shifting between them and where they say
compose we would say acting on the
environment and when they say interpret
we would think of that as sensing the
environment and a lot of their interest
was
in in different context when is it good
to give up agency on your control side
and on your perception side and they
were arguing that um in certain
cultures one is more um appropriate than
the other but it's not consistent across
cultures they were
also uh speculating about what happens
um as your AI is taking over more and
more control over the state of things as
you can see in the bottom right corner
the sort of Pacman figure where the
green is gradually eating up the blue of
the human and so you can think about
that relating to mark of blankets and
saying well you know which states is it
important for the human to continue to
have control over
them okay we mentioned forward
models in active inference in a human
computer interaction context we're going
to need to have forward models of human
perception we going to have to forward
models the computer sensing process
we're also going to need to be able to
predict the human motor control system
what it's capable of and the reliability
of the computer displays given the
environment an
interesting observation is obviously
that active inference focuses on forward
models and it doesn't need explicit
inverse models which is a difference
from um other
contexts okay so
um we want to look a bit at prediction
so active entrance agent aren't reacting
directly to the sensations they're
reacting to their beliefs about future
states of the world and the observations
are there to correct the estimates of
these beliefs so we're trying to
minimize our future
surprise um and you've got
the the standards um approaches of
expected free energy and potentially
breaking that down as Information Gain
and the pragmatic value and the
interesting question is how humans are
going to experience this so if a system
is acting to gain information about them
um they may experience it as a proactive
system that's giving them a personalized
way to interact or it may be that they
find that the system's moving into the
uncanny valley where they're feeling it
distinctly creepy as it tries to pick
their brains about what sort of a user
they are so it's going to be interesting
to see how that the implications of uh
curiosity in the Information Gain term
are perceived by users when they start
to interrupt with the
system but we also think that the the
whole approach of using surprise
minimization as a guiding principle in
interaction design is going to give a
give us a normel perspective on the
design process and may lead to some
surprising uh outcomes in terms of uh
final system
design okay preference prior there
obviously another key element of active
inference and researchers in h have
highlighted that most uh concepts of
interaction don't tell us much about how
intentions are formed or affected by
interaction and it's interesting to
think about how active inference manages
this how the preference priors are going
to be designed because obviously our
systems behavior is going to be a
function of the preference priors that
we give the system and what we assume
about the
user and there's more recent work in
active inference about adaptation of
preference priors during inter action
and it's going to be interesting to
think about how that models but that
seems like an area that's still quite
open for development and we be curious
to hear how the community is evolving in
that
direction okay um and there's you know a
lot of people in human computer
interaction have been used to using
objective reward functions and
reinforcement learning and so there's
interest in contrasting the active
inference approach um this distribution
of preference priors uh compared to
classical control
laws okay challenges is not going to be
easy
obviously there are huge computational
challenges in active inference with the
sorts of complexity of system we're
looking at we're going to have all the
complexity of action rollups we're going
to have to uh balance the performance of
the final system with the real-time
requirements of online applic ations and
it's going to be interesting to see how
much we can continue to use sampling and
research and how much we have to move
towards advertised algorithms where
we're learning a mapping from offline
Behavior even if we can't get real time
go work going we do still think that
offline analysis of these mutually
interacting active inference models can
be interesting for the design side we're
essentially G you know creating digital
twins of our human and system and
observing how they interact with each
other um another challenge we feel at
the moment is that the software
infrastructure for active inference is
still lagging a long way behind for
example machine learning so having easy
to share standardized software libraries
that people are familiar with uh and
having the correct computational
abstractions to build reason about
interfaces is not there yet so we need
to develop workflows where we can
actually apply active inflence to
interaction in a predictable
way um as we just mentioned preference
modeling is A New Perspective for people
in human computer interaction in terms
of using distributions so we've got
these flexible Frameworks but they're
unfamiliar to designers and the
consequences of changes to these
distributions will have significant
effects so how do we work with that how
does it manage the uncertainty in and
the heterogeneity of human behavior
here um and in general with interfaces
representing
uncertainty has the potential to make
interfaces more of us because we know
that we have that uncertainty there
ignoring it is not an option but if we
create probalistic
interfaces users May struggle to
understand what's going on so creating
the right metaphors mapping the
uncertainty into usable feedback for the
users is going to be a major challenge
prediction is obviously key for active
inance and that can potentially mitigate
latency in the interaction Loop but that
predictive aspect of it could be
unsettling for users it may make them
the interface feel like it's in this
uncanny valley where it's sort of human
but not
quite um we were we've been speculating
as if we have a pair of active inference
agents they're going to be trying to
push the joint system into a mutually
predictable region so that even if their
predictive and generative models are not
yet completely capable over the entire
range they're going to be if active
inference is the right framework to
think about things then the two agents
are going to be pushing each other into
a mutually um predictable
space so that could mitigate some of the
challenges that we've just been
outlining um in terms of preference
we're going to have to develop how we
elicit and validate pres preference
priors for design purposes how we can
get generalized preferences from
Individual user preferences but
potentially creating hierarchies of
preferences okay lots of the criticism
of an active inference approach from the
ACI Community would be similar to other
computational simulation approaches
you've got the cost of and complexity of
developing
models the general difficulty of
creating models which can represent the
cognitive and perceptual qu complexity
of humans and especially the sensitivity
of human behavior to the defined details
of
context but you know this is something
that's been around a challenge that's
been around for a long time and Thomas
shared in one of the people's been
working in this field since the 60s has
made the point that you know actually
the process of modeling forces you to
really think hard about what you're
considering and to ask and answer
questions about what the essential
features of the structure and function
are so in terms of changing the approach
to an HCI to doing
science forcing yourself to create good
generous and models is an important part
of thinking about and understanding the
problem so the modeling that's required
by active inference requires you to
think about what are really important
features and if you can build generative
models that validate against user
Behavior you've got an assd test of
whether you really understand that
interactive
system but of course any adaptive
intelligent system is going to have to
deal with Co adaptation of users and
you're going to have to adapt for
account for recursive theories of mind
so we're facing really challenging
things because even humans sometimes
struggle with predicting what
they're um the people they're
interacting with are actually thinking
and what's going on in their
heads okay so active entrance faces the
challenges but you've got that inherent
capacity to model those the user in the
computer in an interaction Loop and then
try to approach the problems
computationally okay so in general we're
seeing active inference as an example of
the
broader um area of simulation
intelligence in HCI um if you haven't
heard of the term simulation
intelligence there's a very good um
archive paper on it it's about 80 pages
long but uh um it goes through how you
can bring different types of simulation
model
uh
into uh understanding the world and
making better models of it and we see
active inference is very much an example
of this you've got a number of different
fields coming together which are letting
you build a computational human computer
interaction approach and you that can
include um interdisciplinary approaches
you've got probalistic programming and
predictive models you've got physics and
for machine learning you need to take
Dynamics and control systems into
account and you've got the physiology
and cognitive science of the human side
of it so you're simulating the the whole
interaction loop from perception
cognition motor control sensors
computation display um and you're built
doing that in a way that's computational
computationally implementable and
testable and we had some previous work
based on non-active inference approaches
um which was published at the the Wist
conference um over a couple of years and
This Is Us simulating
human uh motor control and perceptual
systems so there's a
simulated ocular model simulated muscle
models and then that was using
reinforcement learning to perform
certain tasks and it was the user in a
Box model that you could simulate we
would like to extend that work to
include active inference for the
Future
Okay so one of the things that we're
arguing is an important part of this
framework is that having act to
inference models of both the human and
the the system let us model the
intertwined action of human and system
um and it's
avoiding the problems that were seen
when people tried to bring classical
control models in where you could
exchange building blocks in and out
assuming nothing else would change
because already in the
1960s mcre and his colleagues with their
crossover model demonstrated that human
Pilots would adapt their behavior to
shape the properties as a closed loop so
that if the aircraft properties changed
they would become different Pilots they
would behave differently so that the
closed loop system had a consistent um
shape um and whole Nagle joint cognitive
systems approach highlighted the need to
examine the joint system rather than
individual
blocks um so he was viewing the human as
an implicit model of the process they
were controlling so we can't understand
interaction either from the user or the
technology in isolation you have to have
this joint model and we think that the
sort of active inference Mutual
interaction model are going to be
required to actually model Concepts like
agency or engagement in
interaction so let's have a look at
Outlook
um
we moved into this area
because generative modeling is at the
core of active inference and the massive
advances that have been made recently in
generative machine learning uh make it
possible to do the sort of analysis of
the human perceptual system that would
have been
impossible even 10 years ago um so the
whole General before we started working
with active inference we were using
things like perceptual control theory
and to build systems so we were taking a
closed whp approach are looking at um
empowerment approaches you palan's work
uh where you're modeling the channel cap
from the actuation to the sensing but
these control-based approaches were only
only become realistic if you can model
human perception and that's what machine
learning has provided us with in recent
years active inferences flexible
preference priors and continuously
adaptive behav Behavior we think is
going to be well placed to support AI
tool
use and we've highlighted the
implications for HCI Theory so having
this whole Loop model gives us the
potential to model agency engagement
although there are going to be
challenges in getting there an active
inference gives us this probalistic
predicted unified approach to closed
loot modeling that um we think could be
quite a clean representation of the
problems we've highlighted that there
are bit major computational challenges
in getting things going especially in
real time if it's a good theory of
behavior but not yet practical for Real
Time use could it be used as a better
user in a Box model to help us in the
design process offline and there are
going to be interesting questions about
when to advertise you know the
computation into some hardcoded
nonlinear
network but of course you know we've
given you one example during this talk
of an interactive application but we
want to Branch out within our project
and test it in a wider range of
interactive applications because that's
how we think we're going to H
progress so that's us hitting the
end and I'm going to just put up one
thing that we had good feedback from
reviewers about was our onepage
visualization of active inference and
you can see that um developed in the
actual archive paper itself um but some
people thought that was a nice wage
percentage so we'll leave that up while
you ask
questions okay thank
you awesome all right Anin want to begin
with some Reflections or
questions uh yeah first of all thanks
very much uh for your talk it was really
interesting uh I'd also like to Echo
what the reviewer said uh this is a
fantastic introduction to active
inference if you do not know how it
works um really clear figures clear
explanations uh if you're about to start
reading say the par textbook I would say
have a look at this first and then go to
the textbook it's a really just nice
primer so uh thank you for that like
genuinely education and communication of
how active inference works is really
hard so it's really nice to see good
examples of how to communicate those
ideas very clearly um in terms of my
questions I have loads uh Daniel if
there are questions from the chat
definitely interject and put those in as
well or I will just monopolize all of
the time um but to start with I think
what I wanted
to
uh start with um is in terms of the
alternative SS of inference that you've
experienced before uh what were their
key limitations that you think active
inference is completely like overriding
and what are the limitations where
active inference is also going to
struggle so you know I did mention the
things like perceptual control theory
you know where you're seeing you
behaviors the control of perception so
there's a lot of the the general ethos
of active inference already in there but
they were not so Behavior perceptual
control theory wasn't explicitly using a
problem holistic approach um and it had
you know the standard reward function so
there are lots of you know lots of
different areas where people have got
elements of it so the the active or the
empowerment approach where you're
modeling the the channel capacity from
your actuators to your uh sensors that's
essentially say how much can I put into
the world and predict what's going to
come so that's relating to generative
models so there are similar points there
but active inference has a nice coherent
framework um we're still trying
to understand
ourselves what the relative merits of um
you know free energy and expected free
energy and free energy of the future and
so on all the the variants that could
come in there as an actual cost function
are so that it feels like there's
something interesting there with the
preference prior giving you more
flexibility but we don't you know we
need to see that making an improvement
on a concrete case and understand the
difficulty of how to specify those par
because when you're not just trying to
describe a natural system and actually
create to design a system that's never
been made before you have different
possibilities
and um it's it's potentially taking
active inance out of its Comfort Zone in
terms of not just describing natural
things but saying is this a good design
approach so not not sure I've answered
your question but if John or Sebastian
have other ideas to answer it
better yeah we've done quite a lot of
work on say basian models in HCI um but
that's usually about how we model the
absorption of information from the
environment solves a perception problem
um and one of the nice things about
active inference is that also includes
the acting as part of it pring so it
really has the whole interaction Loop
can be unified in in that that model I
think that's one of the big advantages I
think also the predictive aspect so not
always being about modeling what is
happening now that is really important
in in human interactions you have to
deal with latency and the fact that
people are also making mutual
predictions most other models don't
explicitly account for that and I think
that's something which active inference
does very well and there you know so
there are some approaches like
computational rationality where people
focus on every area will have its own
focal points
in computational rationality there's a
lot of focus on what are the cognitive
bounds or the physical bounds of the
human how does the environment have you
know constraints and these would all be
represented by the generative
models
um um an active inference also the
community has focuses on more on say the
mark of blanket aspect which is maybe
underplayed in other areas and so that's
interesting from an analytic perspective
if you're trying to do understand things
of systems and say well what is the
system and how does that change over
time and um how should we infer that so
again how do we we can take the general
ideas of a mark of black but actually
making that work reliably doing the
statistical analysis to be able to
actually say okay no we can actually
infer this but actually how much data do
we need to do that and how reliable is
it going to be seems still be an open
question but it's that's an aspect
that's not been a focal point of other
areas
anything
okay so fantastic um next question um
but maybe we could also talk about the
the vignettes at the end of the paper
and the appendix because I think they
were very instructive but I'll ask this
question and then maybe you could talk
about the vignettes in relation to this
question which is what do you see as a
difference between computation and
cognition when it comes to these sorts
of uh computer assistance for humans to
use not sure I understand the question
but if any of you understand it better
or think you understand it then how we
go what you so I'm not sure I understand
I sorry that's right maybe maybe I'll
come with an example um so let's say I
have a
calculator that as a tool can help me
compute but I wouldn't necessarily say
it's taking away it's not shifting that
line of control that you spoke about
before okay right right okay whereas we
could extend the sort of this create a
spectrum say where there's a tool where
let's say it's a a large language model
power chatbot where I could ask it to
tell me something or do something for me
and that's going
to
maybe you know takes the example of the
Smart car so you know you might have
your smart car in a full manual mode and
then you're having to pay attention to
everything in the world and you know
you're having to make sure that you stay
in your lane that you keep your speed um
you know appropriate for the other cars
around you and safe and so on and you
have to be aware of
the uh how slippy the road is icy or wet
or dry or Sandy um if you move into a
semi-autonomous mode where the system
starts to do Lane following you are now
relieved of the you know the the
computer can do the computation of
tracking the the white lines in the road
and making sure that you're in a safe
distance from them in both sides and
safe distance from the car in front so
you're relieved of having to monitor
those states in the world and you can
potentially use that spare capacity to
do something else and think a bit more
about where you're actually trying to go
or whether to change your route to so on
so that would be an example of giving up
one bit of agency so that you could um
focus on others we had the smart speaker
example and that could be combined with
the car so there the smart speaker could
make decisions about what to
play um now you could have something
like a control a dial where you could
gradually move through different genres
of content and have much more control of
what exactly was going to come up next
but if for example you're trying to
control your car while also picking
music you maybe need to give more
autonomy to the the music player and
just let it play something roughly in
your direction rather than trying to
micromanage it because you've got to
keep your eyes on the road so it's this
divided attention you know where what
are you paying attention to at what time
and what's a reasonable amount of
attention to pay that it would be unsafe
to focus on the music system when you're
supposed to be driving and so active
inference could help uh in predicting
what you're doing what your loads are
what your limitations are and if you're
spending too much time paying attention
to the interface it needs to take
control and take that away from you so
that you can focus on the
road does that make
sense yes
yes uh next I'm just going to go through
my list um sort of in the order as we
talk spoke about some things and I'll
also pull some stuff from the review
paper as well as well um but yeah if you
feel like there's anything else that you
didn't get a chance to speak about that
you'd like to put in then by all means
do so uh so my next question is um on
the The Uncanny Valley aspect that you
mentioned before I think one of the
vignettes was talking about uh like sort
of the like I think referred to like the
sealed parro product um not necessarily
by name but this idea of uh a robot that
can anticip at your emotions and your
emotional state uh and try and behave in
a way to make you feel better right yeah
um and that's that's a product that has
historically I think the designers of
that said they started with a dog and
the reason they the dog was not
successful as a robot product to help
people feel better was because people
have very strong prior beliefs about
what a dog is how it looks how it feels
how it sounds how it should
behave and that immediately put it in
the uncanny valley because it sort of
looks like that but it's not and then
that difference between your observation
and your priors uh presumably gives you
a very large uh free energy uh Gap and
that is
uncomfortable um so um I think it it's
very interesting to see how if you have
if you sort of make your robot more uh
predictive and able to handle
uncertainty how that would actually
create an uncanny value effect um in my
mind it would actually reduce that
because it's able to better match your
priors if it has a model of you does
that make sense yes I think I think it's
um it's going to be obviously as you you
you know if we get to the goal of you
know Fantastic Model of U everything
then you know then hopefully things
would be good but the as you're moving
towards that goal there's going to be
mismatches where
it's slightly wrong and it's whether
people find those glitches on the way to
you know so if you had somebody who's
willing to stick with it no matter how
creepy it was on the way then fine but
it may be that some of the early phases
of that learning process make it you
know it's got some elements of
prediction but it's it's creepy enough
that you just don't want to touch it it
feels like uh you maybe it wriggles the
wrong way and uh you just go oh my God
what is this alien thing and I don't
want to touch it and and so it never
gets the rest of the information it
needs to improve his model and it's the
same with in general with HCI so we we
were talking about this in in Copenhagen
um a week or two ago and there was a
question about are are designed agents
compatible with the free energy
principle because you know they they
don't die and so on but any any app
which is not good is going to get binned
and any product any robot that is too
creepy is going to be switched off and
ignored so um death for an agent is
being ignored uh and being thrown in the
bin essentially so it's trying to do
things to avoid that drop in its uh
ability to act in the world so it wants
to if it's a if it's been designed to
work well with the human then it should
you know the human
preferences should be key to it but it
also wants to be able to continue to
work with the human in order to help the
the human and if it does something which
gets it bined then it's never going to
be able to improve the human so that's a
very black uh hole in its predictive uh
Horizon that if it thinks there's a
chance that you could be bin for
behaving this way that's going to be
something it wants to avoid so I guess
it's the question is
will we hit it on cany valleys when we
on the way to Perfection when we're
still making errors and we haven't quite
got the model or is it just already very
weird if if humans you for humans seeing
uh a computational object that seems to
be getting them so well will that
already you know be something that
throws people and they they don't you
know it's partly also how quickly can
the human adapt their model of the world
so there may be some humans who've never
experienced a machine that could
understand them the way this one does
and that's already hard for them to
adjust to so um they just say no this is
not a world I want to be in where you
know machines behave like this so that's
I think we're going to
see different things from different
cultures different communities depending
on your upbringing what your
expectations are whether you can
grasp a machine that seems to understand
you in some ways better than you do
yourself because it may be able to
measure aspects of your behavior and
compare that to huge numbers of other
people and maybe it picks out some
things that you're not aware of
yet which would be potentially scary for
some people absolutely no there's
definitely very strong ethical
considerations uh going into this uh
especially considering what do you
explicitly model and what do you
implicitly model and as you alluded to
there the the group priors and then
going for specific priors on a
individual
user um certainly what comes to mind
when you're talking about products and
going extinct the the extinction pre
pressure is uh one one tool that did not
have to my knowledge at least any
predictive power but was very much
largely a rule-based tool was the
Microsoft clippy assist when you were
typing in Microsoft Word and goes oh it
looks like you're trying to write a
letter which I think universally
everybody found not necessarily creepy
but just incredibly
irritating um so I think that's that's
where I sort of see us moving away from
is these very like simplistic assistance
with very limited perception we go to
something that's more probabilistic more
sophisticated oh sorry clippy was the
team you know the original work there
was the you know the basian reasoning
team and Eric corvit and Co were
uh doing the original work but I think
the problem there was it was taken away
from the
basian uh reasoning team and given to a
product team who just said bugger that
we're going to clip all these things and
make it much more straightforward and
then you know they didn't have the the
richness to actually cope with the
complexity of the environment
yeah
okay um could I ask a question about
um the
the in sort of the experiences your team
has had in actually implementing active
inference uh the nois the noisy ordinal
task
selection um experiments as well um so I
know part of the challenges that you
raised was uh sort of
the um not necessarily mature software
toolboxes that we have for implementing
active inference so things like PDP RX
and fur these are probably the most
advanced
implementations out there for active
inference uh do you mind if I ask what
your team was using um and where you see
the biggest challenges from the software
implementation
side yeah so we we looked at pmdp and we
did use it in some preliminary
experiments but uh at the moment or at
least at the time we were looking at it
it was very much limited to um discrete
um probability distributions and so as
soon as you get into very high
dimensional State spaces you reach the
Cheng that you have a combinator
explosion of discrete bins in that state
space and so it will become very very
costly very
quickly um and so we were looking at
alternative approaches and we don't lose
use Julia at all um so RX and fur wasn't
really something we were looking at in
in much detail um and so we just decided
to start
implementing um some of these things
ourselves and because we'd been working
with probabalistic inference tools
before we thought we were sufficiently
capable of doing that um but then
actually you know deciphering the active
inference equations the expected free
energy and so on uh from the book was
more challenging than we thought I think
um and so in part it was also a useful
exercise to actually do the programming
ourselves to see you know do things
actually work the way they should and
now we implementing the right thing here
um yeah so the short answer is we use
our own implementations but very much
with the idea that you know as we work
through more and more uh specific
examples we end up with more robust
implementations where we hopefully can
you know slot in categorical
distributions and swap them out for
practical filters or discussing
distributions and different inference
algorithms um always depending on you
know what's what's demanded by the
individual um uh application that we
want to
build Daniel I think you can probably
speak more found it we've been surprised
at how challenging it is to do what
things that we think should be simple so
you know so it's it's been taking us
longer to get you know we're building a
basic Mouse model expanding we had
control model predictive control-based
models of mouse movement um in previous
papers before we started using active
entrance and we thought it would be
relatively straightforward to take the
active inance approach to that but it's
taking us longer to get things going
there than we expected so yeah so
implementing things in you know
continuous space is uh is is interesting
and as soon as you get something
concrete you start to go okay so what
should the preference um prior be on in
this you know so is it the selection
process is it the movement process
should we have hierarchies of them you
know so it becomes a it makes forces you
to suddenly go okay there's a lot more
complexity here than we thought mean
initially I must most of my experiences
with the discret models and uh P DP
specifically um but I think Daniel can
probably speak to more of the the RX and
fur side and the Julia side and I think
they have pretty Advanced ways of
handling the continuous distributions
particularly for the the Drone flying
examples that they have um Daniel I
don't know if you want to add anything
on
that yeah um I really resonated that a
lot of the considerations of cognitive
modeling independent of whatever
implementation approach are like what
slice or what joints of nature do you
really want to model so that was a a
cool constructivist approach that you
took with building up that biophysical
realism um and then when it comes to
implementing active inference it's a
it's a great learning experience to
actually try to implement in limited
cases different equations and then that
helps like pull back the curtain and
realize like hm we're not really dealing
with a collected data set
and then training a generalized
statistical model to interpolate
something about the patterns of that
data set but rather explicitly stating
certain distributions that might have
observability or non-observability or
control and and so it's like pulling out
those islands or the icebergs that you
want to
model
explicitly rather than it it just it's
like etched away or revealed from where
in another way of modeling you could
have just collected the Salient data set
and then
interpolated not needed to specify
anything specific just we
have Trace data on experiences that were
rated positively or negatively we
trained a model and that's how we are
continuing to classify these traces of
data versus it's like wow there can be a
lot of steps and a lot of degrees of
model or freedom in determining what
which explicit distributions are
relevant for that it's it's a separate
question then like which data set is
relevant for it but but that's it comes
up all the time in in
modeling and uh the frontiers of the
software development are also quickly
moving hopefully meeting up with the
these more modular
challenge
areas the only thing I'd add on to that
is uh coming back to I think something
you said earlier rods on it's an acid
test whether you can create an agent
that is successful in these environments
part of that is also actually not even
necessarily if you know you've
implemented the model correctly but just
being able to specify a generative model
for a problem
really does force you to think and I
think that's one of the things that's
been missing a lot from uh the more
traditional sort of reinforcement
learning and deep learning approaches
where it is just get a bunch of data
Chuck it at a neural network and hope
for the best and you s sort of relying
on the fact that well I don't know what
a generator model for this is I don't
have any model of causality I don't have
any explicit model of a user I just
throw some data and I get an output back
out and I think really interesting from
the active inference point of view of
getting explainability from structure
and being able to think about a problem
sort almost like reasoning from your
armchair and saying I'm going to think
about this problem and say the world
acts in a par the world behaves in a
particular way specify those causal
chains and then test that agent out in
the real world afterwards yeah and I
think the you know obviously the key
thing is if you're using your deep
learning to model how a city works with
traffic or how a hospital works or how a
company Works you're usually doing that
in order to do something else more
efficiently and so as soon as you close
the loop using these predictive models
you've changed the city you've changed
the hospital and it's not going is going
to be moved to somewhere where you had
no data before because you didn't have
the ability to control it before so the
you know the act of inference because
it's a closed loop framework means it's
going to then have to adjust to that new
world and that's part of the basic
framework whereas a lot of the the
classical you know big data work was say
oh all we need to do is get lots of data
we can build a model but they were
forgetting that as soon as they used
that they moved the system that they
were trying to optimize to somewhere it
had never been
before and uh their model was then
useless and so I think that's the
interesting bit but the challenge is
okay we close the loop but you know like
control theory
spent decades looking at stability of
closed loop systems and um you know
we're going to have to revisit a lot of
that in active insurance work is yes
we're trying to change things but you
know can we guarantee that this that our
hospital is going to be stable our city
is going to be stable if we put active
Insurance loops around
it and I don't think we can guarantee
that yet can
we lots of interesting um questions in
the chat just read a few in this last
section so Frasier Patterson wrote some
questions hopefully that we will hear
more about in the coming years so let us
continue on some other questions thank
you though
Fraser um Jeff wrote How can
incorporating active inference in HCI
assist user
trust I would say one aspect is
interpretability so if you build
explicit forward models and um some
communicate the belief that the agent
holds uh that is you know the trigger
for the agent taking certain actions and
that could help explain and and thereby
build trust right um this causal chain
of internal belief to Ag and action is
is harder to disentangle if you look at
things like large language models
obviously it now comes in where you know
they make more explicit their sort of
chain of thoughts but I I would say that
that is one maybe one aspect that can
help with user trust so there the
there's elements of it so there's some
bits that would be on the design side so
if we have explicit models and we can
look at a particular interaction context
and analyze it then we can say oh okay
we understand why the system was
behaving the way it was and we can
decide whether that's a good or bad
thing we may still need to create uh
suin metaphor for interaction for the
user where the predictions are fed in
and that can communicate that succinctly
to the user um in some settings if if
this was a you know to say you were
controlling a tanker and an active
inference navigation system was giving
you it could be saying my predictions
about where you're going to be if you do
this thing or this and then you could
relate to that another way it can
potentially build trust is the because
you're closing Loops
to uh you know maximize um your
predictability minimizing your surprise
it can
potentially there might be two possible
interpretations of the user situation
and it could try and do something to
quickly reduce the uncertainty about
which them they were in and then have a
more coherent
uh um feedback for them whereas in other
situations the system would have to say
well if if this was your intention then
this would be happening if this was you
so an active inference system could try
and reduce that uncertainty more rapidly
in order to give a more coherent
um feedback and control so that might be
one way to build up trust that you can
see uh okay it thinks I'm doing this
again it's about the mutual modeling
aspect that we were talking about as the
user starts to become more confident
that they understand the system it can
work with that so if if it understands
that they don't yet have the user
doesn't seem to have a good model of
them if the active inance agent has an
explicit model of the user's model of
that that that model is still quite
uncertain it knows there's not an awful
lot of point in having a very deep
prediction Horizon because very soon the
users going to get so diffus about their
understanding of what's going on that it
maybe needs to spend more effort in the
early stages of improving the user's
model of it so it's maybe it has to
perform some tasks not so much to
achieve the users goals but to help to
reduce the uncertainty of the user's
model of it so there may be uh a stage
where the system just
automatically essentially trains the
user how capable it is and it's also
then improving its model of the user and
vice versa so you may find that um it
achieves trust by going through a
process of reducing the uncertainty of
the mutual models and then they can do
more together and the prediction
Horizons gradually get longer because
they're able to predict each other's
Behavior more
coherently yeah being able to explicitly
disentangle pragmatic and epistemic
value and when are we seeking
to provide preferred Sensations like
staying on the road for the self-driving
car or the songs that are preferred for
a given listener and then epistemic
value can provide learning and updating
it's not needed in every single
situation just taking ad hoc excursions
from blood sugar homeostasis is probably
deleterious but then again it would be
in balance with maintaining it in a
healthy range to understand responsivity
so it's like whether for biological
systems or these more synthetic
informational systems being able to
understand and have an explicit dial and
this is also one of the most challenging
parts of modeling even after you've set
up the pragmatic and epistemic value
terms their balance is like doing
control theory on a seesaw because it
contains a higher order tradeoff with
preference satisfaction and with
learning
Erin yeah I just wanted to come in with
I think the RX and fur team originally
had an application where they were
looking hearing aids and a parameter
tuning and optimization specifically to
help users use hearing aids more because
the situations where you might be using
that hearing aid would require very
different parameters so if you're in a
train station versus in your house your
hearing a would need to be tuned
differently but that's a very difficult
procedure to do so they would have an
active inference algorithm that would
try and understand the uncertainty of
where they user is but deliberately
choose odd parameter choices to learn
about the context to then choose good
parameter values in order that the user
has a good hearing experience um so
there you'll sort of you I think they're
implicitly getting that trust because
the user then just using the product
more as to your original point of if
apps aren't useful they don't get used
and they die um so as a user trusts a
product more or trusts a system more
they are going to use it more um I did
want to come also on to the original
question as well about improving user
Trust
and the uncertainty uh aspect of this I
mean active inference has a very clear
understand like explicit modeling of
uncertainty how do we communicate that
to users in a sensible way you also
mentioned the large language model stuff
in Chaine of thought I think you know
they don't have an explicit un like
model of
uncertainty but they do have a good job
they do a good job of communicating
whether what they're communicating is
actually or not is a separate question
um but they give English language that
people can understand right yeah there's
a lot of work um on how to
represent distributions interactively
and you can have things like Audio
models which are where properties of the
sound can represent the distributions
involved you've got visual models where
you can blur images but I think you're
going to end up with and you can things
like CH you know
so chof faces or CH faces I can remember
chff radiation chof faces where you
could you know have multiple dimensions
of a a face representing a high
dimensional data but you could
potentially add extra properties to it
so I think there's going to be lots of
scope for Creative
metaphor design to represent uncertainty
we've been looking at this on and off
over the years um so that's going to be
something where there's going to be
loads of scope for creat creativity so
we you could separate the
um the algorithmic elements of
estimating your beliefs from the way you
display them to the user and then try
and optimize you know so which ways are
working how do you change it how do you
you know if you're not if a particular
approach is not repres is not
communicating its uncertainty well to
the user then we need to learn better
ways of doing that so there's going to
be an element of datadriven tuning based
on how well people are communicating and
there's going to be an element of just
creative leps of the imagination and how
do we you know how do we take High
dimensional uncertain data and represent
that and just to go back some of these
things have been around for a long time
so you know the basian uh modelers at
Microsoft had to think carefully about
the Wizards you know so if you're doing
something mundane like a printer wizard
there may be
an optimal question to ask next in terms
of um expected uh Information
Gain but it may be it may if you ask a
series of questions which seem to be
about a topic you know are you properly
plugged into the printer um and then it
suddenly leaps away and asks something
about a completely different topic and
then comes back to wires and printing
and you know printer wires and so on the
user may lose trust in it even if it was
a statistically it was an optimal
question to
ask um because the user can't see the
relationship and thinks this thing
doesn't know it's just guessing random
things so there may be an information
theoretically optimal way to ask things
but if you don't take into account the
user's
model then and so if the user is an
experienced user and trusts the system
then that would be an optimal thing to
do if the user is are naive user in
terms of this wizard which is often the
case because things should hopefully not
fail all the time then you have to
assume that they are a bit mistrustful
about products from Microsoft and uh um
that they are willing to just quit using
the wizard if it starts to ask them what
they think of as random question so this
has been around for a long time and um
it's going to be an interesting question
so one of the you know for example in
ter terms of the the interaction between
the the human and the the computer the
reason that we wanted to work on optimal
interaction
mechanisms as a topic is that we think
there's going to be a
very limited set of core features on the
interaction which which can be combined
in different ways with different sensors
and we want to have so a framework that
people can quickly recognize and it's
the way that nowadays toddlers pick up a
a magazine and start to swipe it
thinking it's an iPad had they they've
very quickly grasped the basic ways of
interacting with a tablet and they're
trying to generalize that around the
world and we think that you know a big
part of making active inference and HCI
work well together is going to be
picking appropriate metaphors building
appropriate interaction mechanisms so
that even if somebody is using a a new
sensor for the first time they can
quickly manipulate it and see ah okay it
seems to be mapping to a dial or a SL
and I'm hearing some formative feedback
from the core mechanism that I'm
familiar with and I can quickly adjust
my behavior to um work with the possible
mappings that might be involved there so
it's going to there's going to be a a
co-creation of interaction metaphors at
the same time as the active inference
and HCI come
together well maybe in closing um Ur and
then all the authors how are you
planning to take the work forward and or
what would be on your wish list slash
issues or questions to raise up for
people to explore
more okay well the work is is continuing
forward and U we're we're hiring
exciting New U PhD students some of
we're asking questions which you you
weren't transmitting but we're we're
sure that we'll get a chance to hear
that from them in person so hopefully
they'll be pushing things forward um
but I think the
um this so Aron you can see you've been
voted in as a new
speaker sometimes does that um so I
think the questions that we have for the
community would you know be about things
like um the P um the preference priors
you know how are people working with
that and tuning that and
eliciting that in other contexts and
adapting them learning them from
Behavior because that's all going to be
super relevant for Building Systems that
can interact well as a human and
reasoning about you know what should
should the the priors on the system just
be about pleasing the human should we
have other constraints on them so what
does that mean for something like an
educational app which should know more
than the user about C certain things at
the the start of the process because the
whole point is to change the human so I
think the you know
we're we're excited to hear what's
happening on things like preference
priors on the whole debate about
alternatives to
EF um for prediction because um and what
happens when things have not yet
converged because some of the
assumptions in the
core um cost functions like e are
assuming that the system is already
doing the right thing and what happens
when there's a mismatch at the start of
that process so I think they're getting
more input from people who are
experienced working with these things
would be exciting for us as you have any
anything more you want to add
in yeah I think we still got some
questions around how the learning of the
models happens so how do you learn a for
model particular how do you do that
during uh interaction with introducing
instability um the question is about the
representation of the lowlevel
distributions that things Sebastian was
talking about you can't always work with
uni model models even uh want to do
things in continuous spaces how can we
do that for the kind of distributions we
actually encounter in human computer
interaction and questions about how we
do the the debugging of these kinds of
models what are the Diagnostics we can
apply to see how well these models are
working um and and track that you going
to build them and evaluate them
something which is going to be C to
that I think for me one of the most
interesting things is looking at scaling
so we can scale things up to higher
dimensional user inputs but also scaling
to much higher uh dimensional degrees of
freedom in terms of the system that are
that's being controlled um the time
Horizons over which we reason and uh
that then brings up questions about you
know what do we amortize what do we
actually explicitly model and roll out
uh and whether or not we bring in some
concepts of you know hierarchical agents
and so on so I think scaling for me and
everything around that bit of what's
going to keep me busy for the next next
SL just a just to add there as well I
think the scale free part is
particularly particularly uh a point of
Focus right now so we've had the scale
for active inference paper that um came
out last year um I think there's a paper
that came out this year about the Tre
search and trying to reduce the sheer
comori explosion of policy policies that
you can have if you have a planning
Horizon longer than x so I think we'll
see a lot of uh work addressing those
issues over the next few years uh for me
it's just a case of getting really clear
and reproducible software packages so
that we can make this easy I think
that's that's where that's where the
work will be over the next few years to
just being able to say right create an
agent Let It Go the thought the thinking
should be about how you set up your
generative model and not really about
whether you're using effective free
energy or expected free energy of the
future or generalized free energy I
think that's largely a problem that
should not NE that should not need to be
solved by say designers or human
computer interaction
Specialists I'd like it ideally that the
software is you know sort of uh
batteries included off you go you get
active inference out of the box but then
it's coming up with a model that maps to
your problem maps to the the problem
that you the are trying to solve for a
user um so hopefully uh we get there
sooner rather than
later and I think also
creating tools to you know harnesses to
take these agents and and their vers and
and you know run simulations and analyze
them in different contexts and visualize
what's going on um look at
counterfactual situations and so so I
think if this is if we're doing it all
right then we have the tools to make the
active inference work well but then
we're trying to you know even if it's
understanding a natural system you might
like to put some put it into a
particular context and observe what
happens and doing the tracking of you
know the behavior so the kind of digital
twin element of of this so how do we
build active entrance agents that we can
actually monitor and analyze and say
okay we're now if we want to have
interpretable systems then we we can get
it into a particular context and and
statistically understand what's going on
around it and why is you know is this
down to is the behavior it's the lack of
you know what seems to be a sensible
action there down to an imperfect um
generative model of the world is it down
to Too Short a prediction Horizon is it
that
we're just aren't sensing the world well
enough then that's that's just the limit
of it's doing the right thing the
information it has but so I think uh
creating the tooling to understand and
analyze the models is going to be
interesting as
well well you've created really a
wonderful style sheet and almost a
graphical taxonomy of different settings
where that is coming into play in
cyberphysical
systems which have at least partially a
fully modelable component and so that
plus open-source software development
plus Community feedback and
application it will be exciting to see
where we all
go so thank you again to the authors and
terone for raising the possibility of
the stream so thanks for inviting us see
thank you
bye e